THE NEW YORK STATE TENANTS & NEIGHBORS COALITION RECORDS (APAP198) 1970-2002
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
The New York State Tenants & Neighbors Coalition Records1970-2002 1970-2002
nam_apap198
Tenants and Neighbors is a statewide coalition of New York's tenants and tenant associations that fight for tenants' rights and affordable housing for all people. The origins of Tenants and Neighbors dates to a meeting of tenant and housing activists from across the state in August 1972 at St. Rose College in Albany, N.Y. By December 1974, a formal organization was developed by housing and tenant activists across the state that drew up by-laws and created the original name as the New York Tenants Coalition. The first statewide membership meeting was held in February 1975. In 1995, the organization changed its name to New York State Tenants and Neighbors. T he collection includes: minutes, annual reports, newsletter and other publications, legislative and organizational memoranda, press releases, clippings, video and press coverage.
The New York State Tenants & Neighbors Coalition
29.9
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in the New York State Tenants & Neighbors Coalition Collection were acquired by the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical History
The New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition traces its beginnings back to a weekend meeting in August 1972 at the College of Saint Rose in Albany, NY. Individuals from Buffalo, Albany, New York City, and places in between came to discuss a statewide tenant organization. This summer meeting came in the wake of two major setbacks: the state government approval of vacancy decontrol and, a botched attempt to create a statewide tenants organization. Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller unleashed a relentless onslaught to achieve rent decontrol and in May 1971 his persistence paid off when the exhausted State Senate acquiesced and passed the measure by a one vote margin. The State Tenants Organization quickly mobilized but a January 1972 meeting dissolved into factional bickering.
January 1973 marked the beginning of weekly visits to Albany to lobby both houses of the Legislature and the Governor's office, all of which were Republican-controlled. The lobbyists navigated through a maze of construction equipment scattered around the developing Empire State Plaza and the freshly minted Legislative Office Building and marched into legislators' offices driven to help repeal vacancy decontrol. Their commitment and recalcitrance in the face of equally obstinate legislatures hastened the passage of a bill that allowed public housing tenants to elect representatives to local housing authority boards. The lobbyists' fervor helped them develop the Warranty of Habitability. The crux of this concept is that rent is conditional on the landlord's obligation to maintain their rent units at a habitable standard. Tenants and Senator Douglas Barclay, Republican of Syracuse, rejected an adulterated version of the Warranty Bill in late 1974. But by 1975 the Democrats controlled the Assembly and member Frank Barbaro, Democrat of Brooklyn, sponsored the bill. The Coalition reached out to a vast network of civic organizations and tenant associations for support in lobbying for the Barclay-Barbaro bill and it Governor Carey eventually signed the Warranty of Habitability into law.
In 1973 the group developed an identity and called themselves the New York State Tenants Legislative Coalition. The first year's budget was a modest $3,000 generated from local organizations, but it allowed for the development of letterhead and a growing mailing list.
Members solidified their organization in December of 1974 when forty delegates from tenant and community organizations from Albany, Schenectady, Utica, Syracuse, Westchester County, Nassau County, and New York City convened in Manhattan and adopted by-laws. They changed their name to the New York State Tenants Coalition and the first statewide meeting occurred in February 1975 less than five miles north of Albany in Glenmont, NY. At this inaugural membership meeting, Michael McKee was elected chairperson and Barbara Chocky of the Lenox Hill Neighborhood Association and Maria Markovics were elected downstate and upstate vice chairpersons. Five statewide membership meetings in 1975 and 1976 followed the inaugural meeting. The December 1976 meeting saw members vote to change the organization's name to the New York State Tenant and Neighborhood Coalition.
The Coalition's lobbying efforts paid great dividends in 1974 when four pro-tenant bills became law. Written by Don Wardle and sponsored by the late Senator Walter Langley, Republican of Albany, the Langley Law requires election of two tenants to the board of each local Housing Authority outside New York City. Another victory involved the Preservation of Sound Housing Act, which created obstacles for developers interested in razing rent controlled apartments to build luxury housing.
A Cooperative/Condominium Fair Practices Act suppressed co-op and condo conversions by mandating that 35 percent of tenants purchase before non-purchasing tenants could be evicted. Also passed in 1974, the Senior Citizen Rent Increase Exemption (SCRIE) aided low-income elderly tenants by restricting the percentage of their income going to rents or real property taxes.
These new bills symbolized great measures of progress for tenant rights, but it was the Emergency Tenant Protection Act (ETPA) that highlighted 1974 as a banner year for tenants and created an indelible impact on the landlord/tenant landscape for years to come. ETPA repealed vacancy decontrol for rent stabilized apartments and extended rent stabilization to Nassau, Westchester, and Rockland Counties. While Coalition members welcomed these parts of ETPA, they were disappointed with its other aspects that allowed landlords to seek market price for vacated rent controlled units before stabilizing the rent again.
The Coalition is the nation's oldest statewide housing organization and annual retreats have allowed people from different parts of the state to meet together. Also paramount to the Coalition's longevity has been the Tenants & Neighbors newsletter, which was first published in 1982.
The loss of the Peoples Housing Network weakened the Coalition's presence in upstate New York. Michael McKee served as executive director of the Community Training and Resource Center, which helped tenants groups in New York City. The upstate problem wasn't addressed until 1986 when the Coalition received financial support from the Campaign for Human Development (CHD) for an Upstate Tenant Organizing Project.
The CHD funds helped the Coalition rally forces in Syracuse and Rochester. The Coalition fought to preserve Mitchell-Lama housing by teaming up with the Mitchell-Lana Residents Coalition. This team effort helped prevent owners of moderate-income housing built from the 1950s to the early 1970s, the main years of the Mitchell-Lama project, from exercising their twenty year buy out option. In addition to Mitchell-Lama housing, by the late 1980s low income federally assisted housing developments built under Section 236, Section 8 were subject to buy outs by the owners. The Coalition's forces in Syracuse and Rochester influenced a bill Congress passed in 1990. For the Coalition, this demonstrated the importance of lobbying the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (USHD).
Scope and Content Information
The New York State Tenants & Neighbors Coalition (NYSTNC) records documents the workings of tenant activists in New York State. The New York State Tenants & Neighbors Coalition is more commonly referred to as Tenants & Neighbors. The collection documents the day to day activities of the coalition along with the legislative and lobbying effort that the coalition was involved with.
The bulk of the collection revolves around the legislative materials that the Tenants & Neighbors fought in aid of Tenant rights and protection under New York State and federal law. The collection focuses on rent regulation and laws. Many of the effort of the coalition were to aid the focus of the renters' rights through protest and grassroots activism. Tenants & Neighbors worked closely with other rent activists.
The administrative files series includes materials belonging to many key members of the coalition such as Michael McKee, William Rowen, and Jim Garst. They are often featured in the News Clippings series providing Op Ed pieces and leading protests. The audio visual materials series contains videotapes of The Tenants & Neighbors Show from the late 1980s to 2001, however we do not have a complete run of the show that aired.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series: Series 1: Administrative Files ( 1972-2002), Series 2: New York State Housing Authorities (1972-2000), Series 3: Legislative Files (1974-1999), Series 4: Tenant Organizations & Campaigns (1974-2002), Series 5: Communications (1973-2002), Series 6: Audio Visual Materials (1987-2002), Series 7: National Housing Issues (1977-2001), and Series 8: News Clippings (1970-2001).
Series 1 - Administrative Files
Series 2 - New York State Housing Authorities
Series 3 - Legislative
Series 4 - Tenant Organizations & Campaigns
Series 5 - Communications
Series 6 - Audio Visual Materials
Series 7 - National Housing Issues
Series 8 - News Clippings
Subject and Genre Headings
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; The New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition; McKee, Michael; Landlord and tenant--New York (State); Rent Stabilization Association of New York City; Rental housing--Law and legislation--New York (State); Rental housing--Law and legislation--New York (State)--Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Rental housing--Law and legislation--New York (State)--Periodicals.; Files by Subject; Clippings; Newsletters; Videotapes
Container List
- Administrative Files, 1973-2000, Undated; 1; 4.4
  The Administrative Files series is arranged chronologically.
  The Administrative Files series consists of organizational records, which document the activities of the Board of Directors. These include documents, by-laws and changes, annual reports to the executive committee. Annual financial reports, meeting minutes and materials relating to the annual retreat of the Executive Committee are found in this series. Many files pertaining to key members of Tenants & Neighbors such as Michael McKee, William Rowen, and James Garst are represented in the administrative files series.
  - Statewide Tenant Organization, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - By-Laws, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Finance, 1974-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Community Development in California: An analysis and recommendations for action by the California Department of Housing and Community Development, 1975 September (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership Meetings, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - By-Laws Adopted on December 5, 1975, 1975 December 05 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee Meetings (1 of 2), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Membership Meetings, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Workshop on Redlining, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - NYSTNC Southern Regional Meeting Minutes, 1976-1977; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence with Dennis Keating, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Executive Committee Meetings/ Annual Meeting, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Meetings/ Legislative Committee Meeting, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Membership (1 of 3), 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 20-22)
  - The Good Guys and Gals: Legislative Representatives for Social Concerns Agenda/Minutes, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Good Guys and Gals: Legislative Representatives for Social Concerns Agenda/Minutes, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Retreat with People's Housing Network, 1978 September (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Michael McKee Correspondence with UC Berkeley, 1978 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fifth Annual Membership Meeting (1 of 3), 1978 December (Box 1, Folder 27-29)
  - Certificate of Incorporation under section 402 of the Not-For-Profit Corporation Law, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Dennis Keating Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Committee Meetings/ Workshop Reports, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Southern Region Action Committee Meetings, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Southern Region Meeting Minutes, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Second Annual Retreat, 1979 September (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sixth Annual Membership Meeting (1 of 3), 1979 October 27-28 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Dennis Keating Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee/Legislative Committee Meetings, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - By-Laws, Name Change, Address Change, 1979-1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Annual Statewide Membership Meeting, 1980 January 06 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1980 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Third Annual Retreat, 1980 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Seventh Annual Membership Conference, 1980 November (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1980 December 14 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee Meeting/Annual General Membership Meeting, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Statewide Membership Meeting, 1981 January 11 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1981 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - First Annual legislative Conference, 1981 May 4-5 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Annual Retreat, 1981 September 11-13 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Executive Committee Meeting and Policy Drafts, 1981 September-November (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - William Rowen Correspondence/ Conciliation and Appeals Board, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Statewide Membership Meeting/ Issues Conference, 1982 January 31 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Second Annual Legislative Conference (1 of 2), 1982 May 10-11 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1982 June (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Annual retreat and Membership Meeting, 1982 October 29-31 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Committee Meeting Memos and Briefs, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Executive Committee Meeting and Tenant Protection Workshop, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Third Annual Legislative Conference, 1983 May 9-10 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1983 October 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - William Rowen Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fourth Annual Legislative Conference, 1984 May 7-8 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Legislative Conference, 1984 May 7-8 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Annual Meeting/Retreat, 1984 October 19-21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Annual Meeting/Retreat, 1984 October 19-21 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Annual retreat and Membership Meeting, 1984 October 19-21 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - 10th Anniversary Ticket Orders, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - 10th Anniversary Journal, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 10th Anniversary Party, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1985 April 13 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Annual retreat and Membership Meeting, 1985 November (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Executive Committee Memos, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dennis Keating Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Operations Committee, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Finance Projections and Memos, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1987 April 25 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1987 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1987 October-November (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Executive Committee, Operations Committee Meetings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, Operations Committee Meetings, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Operations Committee Finance Reports and Memos, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Legislative Committee, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tenants Awareness Day Legislative Workshop, 1988 April 18 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Annual Retreat and Meeting, 1989 October (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Legislative Committee Meeting Minutes, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Legislative Committee Meetings, 1989-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Joint Meeting of Emergency and Executive Committees, 1990 March 18 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Executive Committee Meeting, 1990 December 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Legislative Committee Meeting Minutes, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Annual Meeting and Projected Expense Sheet, 1991 February (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Speaker Vallone of New York City Council, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Legislative Committee Agendas and Memos, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Legislative Committee Meetings, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Legislative Reports, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Legislative Committee, 1992 January-February (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Legislative Committee, 1992 March (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Michael McKee Authored Draft on New York State Component of National Housing Policy Initiative, 1992 August 21 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with William Rowen, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Government Correspondence and Press, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Legislative Committee Research for Rent Subsidy Program, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Legislative Committee, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Legislative Committee Meeting Agenda and Legislation Summaries, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Michael McKee/ Empire State Reports and Governor's Housing Conference, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Michael McKee Freedom of Information Request Tenant Advisory Subcommittee, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Tenant Advisory Committee Planning, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Testimony on Domestic Partnership Legislation Letters of Opposition to Senators, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Executive Committee/Board of Directors Meetings, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Michael McKee Correspondence with Governor Cuomo, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Michael McKee Correspondence with Officials, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Special Report by Garst and McKee, Statement by Governor Cuomo, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Strategic Planning, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Rent Control Rulings and Campaign Donors List, 1993-1997 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - McKee Authored Articles and Various Newsletters of Housing Organizations, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Michael McKee Correspondence with Voice of the People, Daily News, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Annual Meetings, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - The Lady is a Mountain Lion, Too: A Biography of Marie Runyon by Michael McKee, 80th Birthday Celebration, 1995 June 13 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Proposal for a New Legislative Strategy on Rent Regulation, Michael McKee and James Garst Papers, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Tenant and Neighborhood Information Service Annual Report/Meeting, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Organizational Budget, 1996 April 1-1997 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Annual conference, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Rent Law Debate, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Finances and Memos on Pataki Budget Cuts, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Tenant's Rights and Organizing Conference "Winning in 1997", 1997 April (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Annual Meeting, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Michael McKee Correspondence with State Senator Guy Velella, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Memorandums Written by Michael McKee, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Propaganda and Inforamtion on Rent Laws, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Rent Campaign, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Michael McKee Memorandums, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Maximum Base Rent Memos and Legislation, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Treasurer's Report/Finance, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Michael McKee Testimony before Westchester County Rent Guidelines Board, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Michael McKee Letter to Mayor Bloomberg, 2002 July 2 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- New York State Housing Authorities, 1973-2000, Undated; 2; 4.6
  The New York State Housing Authorities series is arranged chronologically.
  The New York State Housing Authorities series contains materials relating to the interactions with other New York State organizations relating to Housing within the state. The organizations that are represented in this series are the Rent Guidelines Board, Rent Stabilization Association, and the New York City Department of Housing and Community Renewal, among others. The City of New York and the Conciliatory and Appeals Board files are also represented within this series.
  - Mailings with Housing Finance Agencies in Other States, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Division of Housing and Community Renewal (DHCR) Emergency Tenant Protection Act of 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rent Stabilization Association Brochures, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)